-- How to Play --


Endgame Checkmate Practice allows you to practice playing the end of a game of Chess. This document does not describe the full rules of chess, only those needed for the endgame.

You control the white pieces, and the computer controls a single black piece. The computer's piece is called the Black King. You start with at least two pieces, one of which is called the White King. You must choose one or more pieces with other names, such as Knights, Queens, or Rooks.

You and the computer take turns, each moving one piece per turn. You go first. Different pieces move differently, as described below. You must move exactly one piece on your turn -- you cannot skip your turn by moving no pieces.

A piece cannot move onto a square occupied by a piece of the same color. However, a piece can move onto a square occupied by a piece of the other color. When this happens, the piece originally on that square is removed from the board. This is called "taking" or "capturing" that piece.

While playing, click any white piece to see where it can move. Then, either move it by clicking one of the squares it can move to, or click a different white piece to see where that one can move.

Your goal is to move your pieces into a position such that, no matter where the Black King moves on his turn, on your next turn you would be able to capture the Black King. This is called "checkmate." The game ends at checkmate, so you never actually capture the Black King. While trying to checkmate, you want to avoid letting the Black King capture your pieces, which might prevent you from being able to checkmate. You also want to avoid a position called "stalemate," which is explained later.


How the pieces move:

 ↑
←♖→
 ↓
The Rook moves horizontally or vertically (this is called "orthogonally"). It can move as far as you want, unless it is blocked by another piece or reaches the edge of the board.

↖ ↗
 ♗
↙ ↘
The Bishop moves diagonally. Like the Rook, it can move as far as you want unless it is blocked or reaches the edge of the board.

↖↑↗
←♕→
↙↓↘
The Queen, the most powerful piece, moves like the Rook or Bishop — orthogonally or diagonally.

 • •
•   •
  ♘
•   •
 • •
The Knight moves either two squares horizontally and one vertically or two squares vertically and one horizontally. Unlike the Rook, Bishop, or Queen, it can "jump," meaning other pieces cannot block its movement.

•••  •••
•♔•  •♚•
•••  •••
The King moves one space in any direction. The official rules of chess strictly forbid him from moving onto a square where he could be captured. (In contrast, non-King piece are allowed to move onto squares where they could be captured, which sometimes is good strategy.)


Checkmate vs Stalemate:

In both checkmate and stalemate, the Black King is in a dire position. He cannot move to any square surrounding him, because if he did, then you would capture him. The difference is that in checkmate you could still capture him even if he did not move, but in stalemate you could not capture him if he did not move. Checkmate counts as a win for you, but stalemate counts as a draw.

Here are examples of stalemate and checkmate, with | and - indicating the edge of the board:

Stalemate        Checkmate
  -----            -----
 |♚               |♚    
 |   ♖            |   ♖
 | ♖              |♖♖

In the checkmate example, note the additional Rook, which could capture the Black King even if he did not move.


If any of the information in this document seems confusing, you are encouraged to just play the game and figure it out though experience. This is a good way to learn.

See also the Recommended Piece Sets document. Beginners are encouraged to start with the first piece set, King and Queen vs King. Here is an example of checkmate with King and Queen:
 |
 |♚♕♔
 |
