-- Recommended Piece Sets --


Normal Pieces:

♔+♕ vs ♚
King and Queen vs King
Easy, very common

♔+♖+♖ vs ♚
King and 2 Rooks vs King
Easy

♔+♖ vs ♚
King and Rook vs King
Medium, somewhat common

♔+♗+♘ vs ♚
King, Bishop, and Knight vs King
Hard

♔+♘+♘+♘ vs ♚
King and 3 Knights vs King
Medium

♔+♘+♘ vs ♚
King and 2 Knights vs King
Medium (if the computer played perfectly, it would be impossible, but the computer will not)

♔+♘ vs ♚
King and Knight vs King
Impossible (have fun playing around with this!)

♔+♗+♗ vs ♚
King and 2 Bishops vs King
Either medium or impossible, depending on where the Bishops start

♔+♗ vs ♚
King and Bishop vs King
Impossible (have fun playing around with this!)


Fairy pieces:

King and Mann
Easy

King and 2 Wazirs
Hard

King and 2 Ferz
Hard

King and Champion
Medium

King and 2 Wizards
Hard?? Or impossible, depending on where the Wizards start
3 or 4 Wizards are entertaining too